你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎继续观看PWN学院高级漏洞利用模块
welcome to another video in the advanced exploitation module of pwn college
今天我们要讨论的是原语，具体来说是漏洞利用原语
today we're going to be talking about primitives exploitation primitives to be specific
以这个模块一直在用的例子为背景
in the context of our motivating example that we've been rolling with this whole video series
例子中对堆的使用，在单线程情景下是安全的
this example has heap operations that would appear to be safe in a single threaded scenario
但多线程场景下，是不安全的
but in a multi threaded scenario they are not safe
我们使用了printf和free之间的竞争
and we have already used a race between printf and free
泄漏了线程特定的arena地址
to leak for example the thread specific arena address
具体来说，在上个视频中泄露了perthread_struct的地址
specifically the tcache perthread leak in the last video
在这个视频中，我们将继续深入
in this video we're going to push further
现在已经泄露了perthread_struct的地址
so we've leaked the address of the perthread struct
稍等，我改一下ppt的布局
and hold on let me fix the layout of this slide real quick
好了
there we go all right
现在已经泄露了perthread_struct的地址
so we leaked out the perthread struct
每个被释放后会放到tcache中的chunk
that every freed allocation gets placed in the tcache
它都会被写入chunk第二个八字节中
gets written into the second qword right
使用它并在GDB中查找
using that and looking in gdb
我们看到了一个指向libc的指针
we looked at where a pointer to libc is
我们利用已知的tcache perthread_struct地址
so you use the fact that we know where the tcache perthread struct is
查找在arena元数据中指向libc的指针
to look up where there's a pointer to libc specifically in the arena metadata
为了得到一个
to get a
在线程arena的arena元数据中
in the arena metadata of the thread arena
它就位于perthread_struct之前
which is immediately before the perthread struct
它里面有个libc中的地址
there is an address to libc
所以现在我们知道了一个libc中的地址
so we know the address of a libc address right
接下来呢
so what's next all right
为了找到接下来的方向
in order to really reason about what's next
我们需要一个最终目标
we need an end goal right
先假定一个最终目标
and end goal let's arbitrarily
当然，到那时一切都会清楚的
of course it'll all become clear then
我们想获得flag
but let's say of course we want to get the flag
但没有一个便于我们获得flag的win函数
there is no convenient win function that will give us the flag
换句话说
or putting in other ways
简单地修改程序逻辑，无法实现目标获得flag
we can't suddenly corrupt the logic of this program to give us the flag to achieve our goals
我们要完全控制这个程序
so we want to hijack the program completely
我们这样做是因为没有
we do this because there is no
因为所有的保护机制都启动了
because all the mitigations are on
栈是不可执行的，等等
the stack is non executable etc etc
我们只能用ROP来控制这个程序
our remaining path forward is to use a rop chain to take over the program
拼凑gadget来泄露出flag
and piece together gadgets to leak the flag
为了做到这一点，我们需要
so in order to do that we need to
或者说，知道libc的地址很有帮助
or it really helps to know where libc is
所以接下来的一步是找到libc的地址
so let's say our immediate next step is to figure out where the address of libc
libc被加载到进程内存的位置
where libc is loaded in memory in the process
幸运的是，我们知道libc中的一个地址
luckily as i said we know the address of an address of libc
在线程arena元数据中有一个指针，指向libc中的main_arena
in the arena metadata there's a pointer back to the main arena in libc awesome
为了利用这一点，我们将
so to exploit this we are going to
或者说，为了向泄露flag迈进一步
or to get closer to leaking the flag
我们将在这节课中讨论
we are now going to in this lecture talk about
我们所谓的任意读原语
what we are going to call an arbitrary read primitive
我们将用它找出libc的地址
that we will use to figure out where libc is
那么什么是原语
all right so what's a primitive
这里漏洞利用原语
a primitive is an exploitation primitive
大意是
is a word that basically means
一种攻击者可重复使用的功能
a reusable capability that an attacker can use
它通常组合利用了一堆漏洞
through often by combining a bunch of vulnerabilities
通常是以复杂的方式，通过组合一堆程序逻辑，误用等等
and often complex ways by combining a bunch of program logic misusing it etc etc
来实现一个单纯的目标
to achieve a simple goal
原语有各种各样的
primitives come in all shapes and sizes
但常见的有任意读原语
but common ones are an arbitrary read primitive
如果你有一个任意的读原语
so if you have an arbitrary read primitive
这表示有一个可复用的功能
that is an reusable capability
它能让作为攻击者的你泄露任意地址的内存
that will allow you as an attacker to disclose memory at an arbitrary address
还有任意写原语，有时称为写-什么-到哪里
arbitrary write primitive sometimes known as a write-what-where
能让作为攻击者的你
will allow you as an attacker
将受控数据写入受控地址
to write some controlled piece of data to some controlled address
还有任意调用原语
an arbitrary call privilege
如果作为攻击者的你
imagine if you as an attacker
覆盖了一个稍后会被调用的函数指针
overwrote a function pointer and that was later called
能让你调用任意函数
will allow you to call arbitrary functions
有各种各样的原语
there are all sorts of different primitives
例如，能将零写到任意地址的原语
you might have a write zero wherever you want primitive for example
但最想要的还是任意读、任意写、任意调用
but the kind of holy grail is arbitrary read arbitrary write arbitrary call and jump
也有一些替代品
there're also relative alternative
有时运气不够覆盖一个指针
sometimes you're not lucky enough to overwrite a pointer
但正好可以覆盖一个偏移值
you are however lucky enough to overwrite a offset
或者你能控制大小值，之类的
or you can control a size or something along these lines
在这几种原语的相对替代品中
and in these relative alternatives to these various primitives
攻击者可以控制一个要加到指针的值
the attacker can control some value that's added to a pointer
这也是非常强大的
this is also very powerful
但显然没有完全控制指针那么强大
but obviously not as powerful as being able to control a pointer completely
我一直强调，这些漏洞利用原语是可复用的
and these exploit primitives i keep saying reusable
它们被用作构建利用程序的模块
they're used as building blocks of exploits
一个利用程序
and an exploit with these
使用这些原语的过程，就像程序开发
when using these primitives becomes kind of like a program in itself
不再只是读这个，写那个，读什么的
it's no longer just you know read this write that read or whatever
不再只是单纯调用pwntools的send、read_until
send read_until send read_until in pwntools
现在是调用函数，如arbitrary_read并传参数之类的
now you're calling functions arbitrary underscore read with arguments and so forth
它变成了一种软件开发
it's kind of becomes a software development sort of life
但这就是复杂利用程序的制作方法
but this is how complex exploits are made
你实现一个原语
you achieve this primitive
然后把它封装在一个函数中
and then you encapsulate it in a function
这样就能在利用脚本中调它
so you can call in your exploit script
你可以调用这个函数
you can call that function
以便于更简单地思考整个利用过程
so that you can reason about your exploit easier all right
我们来讨论一下任意读
so let's talk about arbitrary read specifically
具体是以这个程序为背景讨论
specifically in the context of this application
这个程序，如我们所见，因为竞争条件，没有安全地使用堆
this application as we saw because of race conditions uses the heap unsafely
单线程，它对堆的使用是安全的
single threaded it will be safe heap wides
多线程，一下就有了问题
multi threaded suddenly we have problems
在动态分配器误用模块中，已经做过了堆利用
so of course you have done heap exploitation in the dynamic allocator misuse module
进行了很多次tcache poisoning
and you did a lot of tcache poisoning
在这里也可这么做
and you can apply that here
想象一下，要tcache poisoning攻击
so imagine tcache poisoning attack
使用malloc free scanf malloc malloc
you use malloc free scanf malloc malloc
哦，我漏了一个free
oh i missed a free here actually
我马上改一下，别误导你们
let me fix that real quick so you're not confused one second
不，等等，我没漏
no wait no i didn't
没误导
i didn't so you
我们重来，仔细过一遍
actually let's run through this in detail
通过恶意利用tcache，能强行获取一个已控内存
basically by abusing the tcache we'll be able to force an allocation that we control
然后我们可以使用程序提供的printf功能
and then of course we can using the printf functionality in the program
读出那个地址的数据
we can read out data of that address all right
看一下如何针对这个消息服务器，完成上述利用
let's see how this will look in the context of this program which is a message server
我们分配两条消息，消息a，消息b
so we allocate two messages message a message b
messages[1] messages[2]
message one message two
我们创建了2个chunk，a和b
so we create a tcache emm allocated chunk a and b
然后将两者都free掉
and then we free both of them right
第一次free将b放入tcache时
and that first puts entry b in the tcache
我们回退到释放b时
let's actually rewind when we free entry b
将b放入tcache，并将该bin的计数置为1
puts entry b in the tcache adds sets the count of that bin to 1
再将perthread_struct的地址放到该内存的第二个qword中
and put the address of the perthread struct into the second 8 bytes of that allocation
顺便一提，这就是我们上个视频中泄露的
this is what we leaked out by the way in the last video
然后将next设为空
and then sets the next pointer to null
因为此时它是这个bin中唯一的chunk
because it is the only thing in that tcache bin
当我们释放存储在message[1]中的a时
when we free a which was stored in message 1
我们实际上是把它插入到该列表的头部
we actually insert that into the head of the list
所以head指针指向a
so the first entry points to a
然后a指向b
and then a points to b okay
然后我们想往a，即消息1中，写入一个任意地址
and then of course we want to scanf into a into our message one an arbitrary address
这将使tcache示意图变成这样
that will then make the tcache conceptually look like this
在这个任意地址处，有一些数据
right at this arbitrary address there's some data
这个例子中，我们要读的是存在这儿的b和c
in this example is b and c that is stored that we want to read
我们有
we have our
我们用指向它的地址值覆盖了a的next
we overwrote the next pointer of a with address to that
现在bin链表可以说是被劫持了
and so now the link list has kind of been hijacked
然后malloc两次
and then of course we malloc twice
当第一次malloc时，a返回给了我们
when we malloc once  we receive a back
注入的地址被写入到了链表的head中
and the injected address actually gets put into the head of the list
当我们再次malloc时
when we malloc again
注入的地址将返回给我们
the injected address gets returned to us
但不幸的是，第二个8字节的会被清空
but unfortunately the second 8 bytes of that address is nulled out
在申请chunk时，它会把存储的perthread地址清零
when you allocate something it nulls out this perthread
当申请一个在tcache中的，已释放的chunk
when you allocate a previously freed tcache entry
正如以前看到的，它将把第二个8字节清空
it will null out those second 8 bytes as we observed in the heap allocation module
到目前为止，还都是babyheap的内容
so this so far is all babyheap
还都是在动态分配器误用模块学到的内容
it's the heap the dynamic allocator misuse module that we have come to know and love
那么任意读取在哪里
so where is the arbitrary read
使用这个printf，我们可以打印出结果
with this printf we can print out the resulting
就是我们想要的目标地址的数据
the data at the address that we want to gain
这就是我们的任意读
and that is our arbitrary read
选一个任意地址，就可以读里面8个字节
we chose an arbitrary address and we can read 8 bytes from it
问题是什么呢
what's the problem
当然，问题在于服务器很小心
of course the problem is that the server is careful
在释放消息时，它会将其状态设置为未存储
when it frees a message it'll set it as not currently stored
如果是未存储，它会拒绝scanf该消息
then it will refuse to actually scanf into that message if it is not stored
相反，它就会scanf
instead it'll just scanf into a buffer does not used anymore in that loop
乍一看，完蛋了（被防住了）
so on the face of it we're screwed
但由于竞争条件，情况并非如此
but that's not the case again because of race conditions
我们要与分配竞争，说错了，抱歉
so we're going to race the allocation no sorry
我们要让scanf与free竞争
we're going to race the scanf against the free
我们希望达到的状态是
and what we are hoping to accomplish is that
当我们free时
when we try to free
我刚意识到，我可以更好地展示给你们看
actually i just realized i can show you this much better
我改一下，这样好多了
so let me do that alright that's much better
我们能用提供的free去竞争
so we can actually race using the free action
它先释放内存，再将stored置0
which frees the message and then sets the stored bit to 0
而scanf会检查stored
and the scanf which checks the stored bit
如果它被置为1，就会写入message
and if it is set if it is 1 actually writes into the message
通过让这两个操作竞争
using by racing these two actions
使scanf运行在，释放内存和stored置0之间
and getting the scanf to run in between the free and the unsetting of the stored byte
然后我们就能利用scanf
then we can actually get a scanf
来覆盖我们之前不能覆盖的地址
to overwrite that address before we are no longer allowed to
我们来实践一下
so let's do that
我们先演示
actually let's do that first
然后我们再看一些存在的问题
and then we'll go and look at some gotchas
好的，这是上个视频的程序
all right so this is our program from last time right
在上个视频中
from the last video where
通过free与printf的竞争，泄漏了perthread_struct地址
we were leaking the perthread struct by racing the free and the printf
现在我们来实现一个任意读
and now we're going to get a read
我们已经泄露了perthread_struct的地址
so we leaked the perthread struct
提醒一下，我们计算出了一个指向libc的指针的地址
as a reminder we actually computed the address where there was a libc pointer
我们把它也打印出来
so let's print that out as well
现在也知道了一个指向libc中main_arena的指针的地址
all right so now you have the address of a pointer into the main arena in libc which is in libc
太棒了
awesome
我们来实现一个任意读原语
so let's get an arbitrary read primitive
我们把这个函数命名为arbitrary_read
and we're just gonna call this function arbitrary read alright
当然，我们要做的类似于leak_perthread_addr
we're gonna of course similar to our the leaking of the perthread
我们将传给他2个连接，用于竞争
we're going to pass it two connections that it'll use to do the race
还有我们想读取的地址
and basically the address that we want to leak right
好极了，除了这些
awesome all right so other than that
我们会按照之前的计划行事
we're going to do exactly our prior game plan
在我们开始之前
before we get started
把管道清理一下
let's clean out the pipes
以防那里有东西在等待
just in case there's something waiting there
导致我们在读取值时出问题
and it'll screw us up when we try to read the value whoops
好的
okay
打包好我们要读取的地址（转成小端序）
let's of course pack the address that we want to read
把这个改成addr
let's make this addr
为了节省时间，我会拷贝我写好的脚本
to save time i'm copy pasting of a script i wrote
这样你们就不用等我打字了
so that you don't have to wait for me to type
还是不要这么做了
but actually let's not do that all right so
如你所见，你需要malloc 2次
as we saw you're going to have to allocate two allocations
我们执行了 malloc 1 malloc 2
we did a malloc 1 malloc 2
这样我们最终会得到一个链表
so that we end up when we free them with that awesome link list
然后我们就可以覆盖head的next指针
that we can overwrite the next address of the first entry of
我们先释放chunk2
we're going to free the second one
再释放chunk1
and then we'll free the first one
当然，我只是依照这里的计划行事
and of course i'm just going by our game plan right here
这是我们的计划
here's the game plan we're gonna have
实际上让我们
and actually let's
这是我们要达到的效果
there so this is what we'll end up with
获得2个chunk，先释放chunk2
gonna get two allocations we'll free 2
我们想让第二次free与scanf竞争，再从这里执行下去
we want to race this second free against the scanf and go from there
我们回到终端
so let's get back to the terminal
tcache中有一个chunk，malloc 1 malloc 2 free 2
so we have one allocation malloc one malloc two free two
然后持续尝试竞争
then we're gonna keep trying to race
这个竞争不容易成功
so the race isn't gonna be extremely likely to succeed
尝试在free和修改store状态之间，切走去scanf
we're trying to get right between the free and the store
这里的指令不是很多
this is not a lot of instructions to get
要在这中间，切出free线程
in which the free thread can get discheduled
执行scanf线程
our scanf thread can get run and so forth
所以我们要运行很多次
so we're going to have to run multiple times
当然，在疯狂fork python进程的同时
and of course simultaneously by using this insane forking of the python processor
我们将发送第二次free， free 1
we're going to send both the free of course that second one
我们要发送它很多次
and we actually want to send a lot of this
因为我们尝试一次又一次的释放它
because we want to have a trying freeing over and over
然后scanf需要命中第一个free
and then our scanf needs to hit that first free
实际上，我觉得不用
actually so i guess this doesn't
其他free没有用
other frees won't do anything
只有第一次free有用
only the first free matters
我们这样做，我们在这里发送一个free
so let's do that so we send a free here
我们再终止这个子进程
we will kill the that same process all right
然后在主线程或主进程中
and then in our main thread or main process
我们会发送一堆scanf
we will send a bunch of scanfs
因为我们要scanf scanf scanf
because we want to do scanf scanf scanf
那个free可能击中其中之一
and then that free that will hit in one of the
一个线程执行free
one thread will do the free
而另一个线程在执行这些scanf
while the other thread is doing all these scanfs
导致竞争，希望能如我们在这张ppt上看到的
will have a race and as we saw on this slide will be hopefully
好的
alright so
发送scanf
send scanf
要输入的idx，不对，我们知道idx
and we want to put in the index no index we know the index
我们scanf 1
we want to scanf one
然后输入打包好的地址，还有一个换行符
and we want to put in our packed address and a new line
乘以2000，好的
times 2000 all right
这里竞争，wait一下
so we hit that let's do wait here
给点时间，处理这些scanf
now let's give everything some time to actually process all of these scanfs
然后看一下攻击成功了没
and then we check to make sure that the attack worked
我们要做的是
so what we're going to do is
我们malloc一下，希望返回chunk的next被覆盖了
we're going to malloc that guy that we hopefully just overwrote the next point
我们malloc一下，拿到chunk a
we will malloc an allocation to receive chunk a
希望我们已经覆盖了chunk a的next指针
hopefully we have just overwritten the next pointer of chunk a
然后我们输出chunk a
we'll printf chunk a then
再取出直到换行符的输出
we'll just retrieve the message up to the new line
最后确认一下
and we'll confirm
我复制粘贴一下，这个打起来很麻烦
i'll copy paste this because it's annoying to type
我们确认一下，这个tcache没清零的next指针
we'll confirm that the next address which tcache doesn't clear out is
当chunk给到我们时
when the chunk gets returned to us
我们要确认一下它的next是否被正确覆盖
we'll confirm that the next address is properly set
如果覆盖成功，就跳出循环
if it's properly set we're done and then we can break
如果没覆盖成功
if it's not properly set
说明竞争失败了
then we didn't win the race
就重来，回到free 1
we're going to free one again
我们刚刚malloc 1，所以这没问题
we just malloced it so that's perfectly fine
然后再试一次scanf
and try again with our scanf
这个竞争有个好处，他很安全
so the nice thing is this race is very safe
即使竞争失败，也不会导致进程崩溃
it will not kill our process if we lose
这很好
which is great okay
当成功后
so when we're done here
我们要再malloc chunk b
we're going to malloc our second chunk b
我们要等它发生
and we are going to wait for that to actually happen
我在这里用clean，我也可以用time.sleep
i use .clean here i could also use time.sleep
clean会休眠一小会
.clean sleeps a tiny bit
这就够malloc一次了
and that's all we really need to get one allocation done
然后再发送printf
and we're going to send the printf
用同样代码解析出目标地址的值
and read it out using this same code
太棒了
awesome
我粘贴一下代码
let me just paste this code and
我们要从小端序转成字符串
we're going to unpack it
取出8字节，转成可读的，返回它
we'll get 8 bytes unpack it and return that
现在有了一个函数
so now we have a function
这个函数会完成一个任意读
and this function will do an arbitrary read
我们可以重复执行它
and we can run it over and over
我们执行一下这个arbitrary_read
let's do this arbitrary read
如果想要main_arena_address
so if you want the main arena address
我们来获取它
let's get it
执行 arbitrary_read(r1, r2, main_arena_ptr_address)
we will arbitrary_read r1 r2 main_arena_ptr_address
我们传入指向main_arena指针的地址
so we send in the address of the pointer to the main arena
就能拿到泄露出的main_arena_address
and we will get back a leaked main arena address
如果第一次就成功了，那就太不可思议了
and if this works on the first try that'll be insane
大概率不会
but it likely won't
sendline我竟然写成了sendfile
so instead of sendline i did sendfile that's weird
我们kill这个进程
let's kill that process
我们先这样
actually here let's do this
我们在启动进程前，先尝试kill一下
we're going to try to kill that process before we started up
太棒了，好的
awesome okay um
sendline在哪里
where's that sendline
你们都没警告我
you didn't warn me
一个都没警告我
none of you warned me
期待你找到它（估计是读评论）
hoping you'd catch it
哦，我开个玩笑
oh just kidding
哦，sendfile在这儿
oh sendfile
太棒了
awesome
好的，我们再试一下竞争
okay we're trying the race
时间比预期的长
taking longer than expected
有时用时确实会比预期的长
sometimes it takes longer than expected
但也可能是一个信号，表明这行不通
but could also so be a sign that it's not gonna work
有趣
fascinating
稍等
oh wait
怎么回事
what was it
停在readline了
it was sitting on readline
sendline我写成了readline
i did readline instead of sendline
不不不，这里是对的
no no no this is right
哦，不不不不，这里没问题
oh no no no no no this is all good
不，不在这里
no it's not here
这里应该是sendline
this should be sendline
好的
okay
如果你看到明显的错误，请说出来
please say something if you saw something that was obviously wrong
我们没竞争成功
we're not winning the race we're not winning the race
哦，这里我没发送换行符
oh i didn't send a new line here
这里应该是sendline
this should be sendline
所以它从未真正开始处理它
so it never actually started processing it
我们再试一下，成功
let's try that boom
我们写出了正确的脚本，我们竞争成功了
we make a correct script we win the race
我们竞争成功了，执行了printf
so we won the race we did our amazing printf
现在我们泄露出了一个指向libc中main_arena的指针
and now we have leaked a pointer into the main arena which is inside libc
我们先看些存在的问题
all right let's get to some gotches
再看看它们的含义
and then we'll look at the implications
有几个问题
some gotches
一是我们有
one is we have
蒙住了
brain dump
一是在泄露libc地址的同时，破坏了堆元数据
one is that we have now corrupted the heap metadata alongside leaking out that address of libc
我们已经将libc里的地址写到了tcache的head指针
we have also set that address of libc as the next entry in the tcache struct right
这意味着如果count不为零
that means if count was not zero
那么下次malloc将尝试返回这个地址
then the next malloc would try to return this entry
再把第二个8字节归零
and then also zero out the second 8 bytes of it
清零Ben（key指针）
to try to null out the beyond
然后用第一个8字节覆盖head指针
and then take the first 8 bytes and overwrite the entry with it
然后下一次malloc会返回这个地址
and then the next malloc would return those and so on right
这样我们就劫持了这个链表
so we've hijacked that linked list
我们需要理解它的含义
and we need to understand it as implications
幸运的是，在这里count为零
luckily in this case the count is zero
所以之后的malloc，将创建并返回个新chunk
so a future allocation will just be created as fresh chunks and given to us
但并不总是这么幸运
but that's not always so lucky
有一种情况
one thing that you can rely on in a situation
就是多线程下，有竞争条件，而且你还能创建线程
where there's multiple threads and there's a race condition and you can create new threads
就像这里可以创建新连接，来创建新线程
like we can create here by creating a new connection
每个线程都有自己的tcache元数据
each thread has its own tcache metadata
Tcache是指线程缓存
tcache means thread cache
正如其名，它是每个线程都有的
it's perthread like this perthread struct implies
如果你断开一个连接，再新建个
so if you just disconnect from one connection and new connect from another one
你就有了一个新的tcache
you have a new tcache and you're good to go
断开连接不是必须的
you don't even have to disconnect from the old one
只需要新建个连接
just connect from the new one
事实上，我们用的两个连接都有自己的tcache
and in fact both of the connections we were using  actually had their own tcache
如果你注意观察r1里的所有chunk，就能发现
if you notice being careful to all the allocations on the first connection r1
另个问题是，message现在指向libc内部
the other problem is that our message is now pointing to somewhere inside libc
我们控制了要读取内容的地址
so we controlled address that we're going to read stuff out of
或者说，消息现在指向了perthread_struct
so or rather our message is now pointing to the perthread struct
而perthread_struct看起来不像chunk
the perthread struct doesn't look like a chunk right
抱歉，它不是指向perthread_struct
sorry it's not points to the perthread struct
而是perthread_struct前，arena元数据中指向ibc的指针的地址
it's pointing before the perthread struct to where the arena metadata that had libc
它看起来不像一个chunk
and that doesn't look like a chunk
它没有chunk的正确元数据
it doesn't have the right metadata
所以当元数据
and so when that metadata
当你试图free它时
when if you try to free it
程序会崩溃
the whole program will crash
因为当free的不是一个合法chunk，libc会恐慌
because libc will panic that what it is trying to free is not a valid chunk
看到异常的size，它崩溃了
it will look at that size and it will freak out
它会中止这个程序
and it will abort the program
解决办法是不要这样做
the solution is don't do that
不要重复
don't repeat it
因为在这里，你不需要
because you don't need to in this case
这里有很多很多的消息索引
there are many many message indexes right
我来演示一下
so let me actually show you
如果我想泄露点别的
if i try to leak out something else
假设，我泄露了main_arena后
so let's say i leaked out the arena
我还想泄露
and i want to leak out something
我泄露了一个libc地址
actually at i leaked out a libc address
还想泄露这个地址里的东西
i want to leak out whatever was there
我没调任意读来泄露
i didn't even leak it out
又大脑宕机了
that was a weird brain dump
main_arena_address而不是main_arena_ptr_address
instead of main_arena_ptr_address just main_arena_address
我们之前的，嗯，好了
our earlier okay there
有时竞争失败，也会崩溃
sometimes the races don't work and we crash okay
开始吧
here we go
正如你看到的，我在试着打印出main_arena_address
i was trying as you can see to print out the main arena address
当我在这里发送malloc 1 printf 1时
and when i sent the malloc one printf one here
它实际上
it actually
实际上，发送free 1，就开始坏起来了
actually when i sent the free one that's when shit really hit the fan
但等发送这个时，它才发现服务挂了，管道已关闭
but it noticed when sending this that the program was dead the pipe was closed
还有一个新的EOF错误
and there's a new end of file error
如果我打印程序输出，它提示我，释放了非法指针
if i read what the program wrote to me says free invalid pointer
让我们在GDB中运行它
let's run this in gdb
perthread struct（泄露）失败
the perthread struct failed
稍等，在GDB中跑一下
hold on run this in gdb
好的，我们泄露出了main_arena
okay we leak the thing we leak the main arena
现在我们要试着泄露
and now we're gonna try to leak
啊，好了
ah and here we go
我们触发了SIGABRT
we got that SIGABRT
回退到调用者，再回退，释放非法指针，再回退
let's go up up up free invalid pointer go up
我编译时开启了调试符号，所以能看到这些
i compiled this with debug symbol so i could show you this
我们当时正在释放messages[idx]
we are freeing messages index
messages[idx]是我们的
messages index is our perthread
首先idx是1，额，2
first of all index is one as emm two
哦，对对对，2. idx是2
oh yeah yeah yeah two index is two
这是我们
that is the index that we
啊，在这里挂了
ah so died here actually even
messages[2] 指向的是已经控制的地址
so 2 is the allocation that is controlled right
我们就是用它指向的在线程arena中指向main_arena的指针
and that is what we pointed at the main arena pointer on our thread heap
这就是它指向的地址
that's where it's pointing
当试图free它时
when we try to free this
当然这里的地址，正是我们讨论的
of course the address here is an address as we discussed
是我们在printf时泄露出的，指向main_arena的地址
is the address we leaked into the main arena when we did printf
这就是我们泄露的信息
and that's in fact what we leaked
但如果我们看一下元数据
but if we look at the metadata
这个chunk的size，它存储在该地址-8字节处
the size metadata of this chunk which is stored 8 bytes back
是0，这不是一个合法大小
is 0 that is not a valid size
当我们试图释放它时，libc就会崩溃
when we try to free it libc freaks out
这并不好，对吧
that is not good right
所以如果可以的话，我们最好能让原语可复用
so we need to make primitives ideally if you can repeatable
再次声明，好的软件实践意味着
again good software practice means that
如果你调用一个函数一次，你应该能够再次调用它
if you call a function once you should be able to call it again
除非有什么明显的变化
unless something obvious has changed
正如这张ppt上说的
so as we see from this slide of course
我们已经把桥烧了
we've burned the bridge
messages[2]指向一个随机的地址
messages 2 specifically is pointing to some random stuff
这是ppt上的一个bug
this is a bug on the slide
我来修正一下，这样大家就不会感到困惑了
let me actually fix it so no one's confused all right
所以messages[2]现在指向一些垃圾数据
so messages 2 is now pointing to some garbage data
也不能说是垃圾数据，它指向libc内，这很好
not garbage data it's pointing to into libc which is great
但它指向的东西看起来不像chunk
but it's pointing to something that doesn't look like a heap chunk
所以我们可以这样修改我们的任意读原语
so we can actually change our arbitrary read primitive
就是每次使用不同的messages[idx]
to use different messages as time goes on
我们更新一下，这很容易
so let's update that this is easy to do
我们只要记录一下当前使用的idx
let's just keep track of what index it's currently on
我们使用格式化字符串
and we'll just put in some format strings
来确保分配或释放了正确的idx
to make sure we allocate and free the right indexes
这应该是一个格式化字符串
this should be a format string okay
这里应该是idx
here this should be index
不幸的是，没有字节类型的格式化字符串
we can't have byte format strings unfortunately
所以我们必须这样做
so we have to do that way all right
这是idx
here is the index
这是idx + 1
and here is index plus one
然后idx + 1被消耗掉了
and then index plus one is burned
意识到，我们不能再将它指向别处
realized we can't repoint it somewhere else
所以现在我们要将idx加2
so now we're just going to incremented by 2
将idx声明成全局变量
let's declare this is a global
为了让python知道要用全局变量idx而不是其它局部变量
just for so that python knows to use the global index versus some local variable
每次调用arbitrary_read时
and this every time you're on arbitrary_read
它会使用一组不同的idx
it will now use a different set of indexes
所以现在我们可以读到我们要的内容了
so now we can read memory to our harsh content
发生了什么事?
what's going on
哦，gdb挂起了服务
oh gdb is hugging things up
我们把GDB关了
let's disable gdb here
好的
alright
哦
oops
泄漏失败了
the leak failed
所以我们可能
so we might have just
可能有bug
we might have left the bug
连续两次泄漏失败
leak failed twice in a row
perthread struct泄漏失败三次
perthread struct leak failed three times
泄漏失败
leak failed
好吧，肯定有bug
okay there's the bug somewhere
哦，忘了将这些字符串改成格式化字符串
oh yeah because we forgot to make these f strings
还有其它字符串忘了的吗
anything else we forgot to make f strings
我不这么认为，试试吧
i don't think so let's give that a try
好的，泄漏成功
okay leak succeeded
第二次泄漏还没有失败
the second leak is not failing yet
不过花了很长时间
it's taking a long time though
发生了什么
what's happening
我一直在尝试，还在尝试
i was trying still trying
发生了什么事?
what's going on
free scanf 都没问题
we free scanf properly
我们重启一下ipython
let's restart ipython
哦
oh
太棒了
awesome
泄漏成功
so that leaked properly
我是说它返回了
i mean it returned
我马上会证明0是对的
i'll show you that the zero is actually correct
刚刚应该是python卡住了
there must have been something stuck up with python
可能是因为我们一直fork进程执行后台任务
probably because of the way that we're just yolo forking to run background tasks all right
这样可行
so this works
任意读原语可以执行多次了
arbitrary primitive works multiple times
我们用gdb看看，来证明给你看
let's grab gdb and actually explore to so i can convince you
好了，test 0x0
alright here we go test 0
该死，我关了它
ah shit and then i killed it
重来
let me restart that
泄露 test 0x0
leak test zero all right
关了它
kill that
这些是messages
here are the messages
这是arena地址
here's the address of arena
能看到有message 1和2
and you can see now we have message one and two
这是用来泄露main_arena指针的
this is what was used to leak the main arena pointer from here
然后是message 3和4
and then message three and four
在message 4中，有地址
and in message four we have the address the
这就是我们泄露的值
this is what we leaked this value and whoops
这是main_arena
here is main arena
main_arena里的头8字节是0
and what is there is a zero all right
这就是任意读原语
so this is the arbitrary read primitive
我们成功了
we did it
我们在这里暂停一下
we are going to pause here
实际上我要提一件事
actually i'll mention one thing
剩下的我会在下一集汇总视频中做
and then i will do the rest in the putting it all together video that's coming up next
我要提的一件事是我们不仅能任意读
one thing i'll mention is we can go actually beyond the arbitrary read
几乎不用怎么改
we can do the same almost the same thing
只是最后不用printf，而用scanf
but instead of a printf we do a scanf
瞬间，我们就有了一个任意写
and suddenly we have an arbitrary write
这并不奇怪
right so it's not so rare
因为这些原语很复杂
because of the complexity of a lot of these primitives
这个原语结合了竞争条件与堆攻击
this primitive is a tricky race condition combined with a tricky heap attack
对这个原语稍作改动就能实现各种功能并不奇怪
it is definitely not rare to have slight tweaks on these primitives that can accomplish multiple things
这里相比任意读
so here instead of an arbitrary read
不printf了，改scanf
instead of a printf we do a scanf
瞬间，我们就能覆盖被控内存了
suddenly we overwrite the controlled allocation
当然，我们就有了一个任意写
of course that gives us an arbitrary write
我们快速看一下
let's take a very quick look
我们只要复制这个
so we're just gonna copy this
实际我们可以粘贴它
and we can actually paste it
改成arbitrary_write
and we can say arbitrary write
所有这些都保持原样
all of this remains the same
除了这个printf改成scanf
except for this printf becomes a scanf
我们想要的是
and what we want
我们不能这样了，要那样
we can no longer use this we need to use something like this
因为这里是字节字符串
cause we need the byte string
所以我们要pack想要写入的值（转成小端序）
we need to pack the value that we want to write
这里声明要写入的值，这里是任意写
i can put the value here and this is arbitrary write
现在可以
and now you can do a
我们做个测试
let's do a test
我们写入41
we'll write four one
我们写入41414141
we'll do four one four one four one four one
到libc中的main_arena地址
to the main arena address in libc
aaaacccc
好的，按回车键
alright hit enter
arbitrary_write接受三个参数，但给了四个
arbitrary_write takes three positional parameters but four were given
显然这不是我们想要的
obviously that is not what we want
哦
oops
我之前改了什么
what did i update
啊偶，我写在这了
oops i put it
这应该是arbitrary_read
this should be arbitrary read
我的错
so my bad
测试
test and
一直在竞争
we are racing we are racing
怎么回事
what's going on
是的，没那么容易，我们忘了
yeah that's not quite so easy we forgot
在任意读中，我们要一直读到接收到MESSAGE
In an arbitrary read we were reading until the message
这里不需要这么做
we don't do any of that
这些都不重要，直接返回就好
none of that matters right we just return
我们执行scanf，没有需要读的
we do our scanf there's nothing to read
回车
hit enter
成功了，我们完成了
it's done we did our read so let's
我们完成了写入，任意写
we did our write our arbitrary write
看看这些信息，太棒了，这有一条
look at the messages awesome here's a message
我们用这个泄露了main_arena指针
ah so here is when we leaked out the main arena pointer
我们用这个泄露了test值，它是main_arena里的0
here is when we leaked out the test value of the main arena which was zero
我们用这个写入了main_arena
and here is when we wrote to the main arena
为什么没写入
and why is it not written
说真的，为什么没写入呢
seriously why isn't not written
啊，因为这不该是idx，而是idx+1
ah because this should be not index but index plus one
我们写入到了错误的地址，写到这里了
we wrote to the wrong message we wrote here
这可不好
that's not good all right
我们再试一次
let's try that again
我们改完了
we fix that up
测试，完成，关闭它
test done boom kill that
以下是我们的messages
here are our messages
写入到了目标地址
get write to the point
用4141414143434343覆盖了libc的一部分
boom be overwritten part of libc with 4141414143434343
任意写，达成
arbitrary write all right
还要说的是，这不是一个好的软件实践
one thing that i will say is that was not good software engineering practices
我改一下ppt布局
let me fix the layout of the slide real quick
这不是好的软件实践
that was not good software engineering practices
现在有大量的重复代码
there's a ton of repeated code that exists right now
就在我刚展示的任意读与任意写代码中
as i just showed you between arbitrary read and arbitrary write
所有这些疯狂的竞态条件
all of this crazy race condition stuff
任意读和写的区别只在于printf还是scanf
actually the difference between read and write is just that printf versus the scanf
当你的漏洞利用代码很复杂时，尽量复用和封装代码
so try to reuse and encapsulate in your exploits as much as possible when they're complex
有些情况不需要
there are cases when it's not what you want to do
比如，如果读和写之间要做的修改非常微小
if there's very subtle differences that you need to make between the read case and the write case
但在我们的漏洞利用代码里
but in our exploit
我们应该封装一个controlled_allocation函数
we should have a controlled allocation function
它能让分配的内存位于受控地址
that makes the allocation at a controlled address
然后基于我们想要读还是写，执行printf或scanf
and then be either printf or scanf based on whether we want to read or write
软件开发技巧在漏洞利用开发中很重要
software development in exploit development is important
从个人经验来看
from personal experience
对于非常复杂的漏洞利用代码，我会准备测试用例
for very complex exploits i have had test cases
因为要尽快找出问题，就和软件开发一样
because you want to catch things going wrong similar to software development as fast as possible
我来演示一下正确的做法
so let me show you the right way of doing this
有两个比较大的函数arbitrary_read和arbitrary_write
so you have these kind of two big arbitrary read and an arbitrary write function
就停在这里
let's stop it right here
这里获得了位于受控地址的chunk
this is where we malloc the controlled allocation
在这里直接返回
and then let's just return
我们在这里更新idx，因为这对该函数很重要
we'll do our index because the index really matters for this guy
然后，这里开始是arbitrary_read
and then here we will arbitrary read r1 r2 addr
这里是controlled_allocation
so this becomes controlled allocation
这里是arbitrary_read
all right and this becomes arbitrary read
我们调用controlled_allocation
so we do the controlled allocation
在这之后，我们得到了一个位于受控地址的message
now after this we have a malloced message at a controlled location
现在我们可以打印message了
now we can print the message
一切都很好
and everything is good
这个变成了idx-1，因为这里idx增加了
this now becomes index minus one because index was incremented
我们实际看的是上一个idx
so we're actually looking at the last index
我们准备好了
and we're good to go
这里也一样
same thing here
只是注意scanf这里是idx-1
just for that scanf becomes index minus one
这里改成调用controlled_allocation(r1,r2,addr)
and instead we do controlled allocation r1 r2 addr
软件实践好多了
much better software engineering practices
确保能运行
let's make sure that they fly
执行，回到这里
run it go back here
好的，第一次泄漏成功
okay first leak works
测试泄漏成功，写入也没有崩溃
the test leak works the write didn't crash
让我们看看这些消息
let's look at the messages
我看着没问题
looks well set up to me
覆盖也成功了
and overwrite is working all right
这就是制作优秀软件的方法
that's how you make good software
我们需要什么原语呢
so what primitives do you need
通常如果有任意读和任意写，你就赢了
typically if you have an arbitrary read and an arbitrary write you win
通常你需要一条信息来开始
you need one piece of information to get you started usually
一般是一个你能通过它泄露东西的指针
and that is a valid pointer at which you can start reading
我们用它泄露了tcache元数据
we use that by leaking the tcache metadata
如果我们只有任意读或任意写
if we had an arbitrary read or an arbitrary write
但没有这个tcache泄露
but we didn't have that tcache leak
我们还是不好弄
we would still be in trouble
因为我们不知道从哪里开始泄露
because we wouldn't know where to start reading
但因为我们能从某处开始读
but because we started reading somewhere
我们现在可以把任意数据写入libc
we were able to you know just now write arbitrary data into libc
能达到这一点，你就完事了
at that point generally you are done all right
这期视频将在此到达尾声
so we're gonna end the video here
在下一个视频中，我们将把所有东西放在一起
in the next video we're gonna put it all together
之前讲到全部，来获得flag
everything that we just did into the flag
到时见
see you there